{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This group was the first target of Justinian’s reconquest wars. These people, along with the Alans, were led by Genseric. These people captured Carthage in 439 AD, making it the capital of their North African empire. Pope Leo I was able to limit, but not stop, these people’s 455 sack of Rome. For ten points, name this Germanic tribe whose name has become synonymous with defacing and destroying property.",
      "answer": "Vandals"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one scheme, this man attempted to negotiate a secret rebate with railroad companies by creating the South Improvement Company. A company founded by this man was subject of a muckraking expose by Ida Tarbell. This man grew his business through horizontal integration after establishing a series of refineries in Ohio, but his flagship company was eventually broken up by the Supreme Court in 1911. For ten points, name this founder of the Standard Oil company.",
      "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2012, this country temporarily occupied the Heglig oil field of its northern neighbor. The President of this country has been known for his fondness for Stetson hats since he received one as a gift from George W. Bush in 2006. Civil war broke out in this country in 2013 shortly after Riek Machar was accused of plotting a coup d’etat by President Salva Kiir. For ten points, name this African country that declared its independence in 2011.",
      "answer": "Republic of South Sudan"
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this position, John Lindsay, switched parties to mount a failed bid for the Democratic nomination for President in 1972. Norman Mailer ran on an Existentialist Party ticket for this office. This office’s occupants, including Fernando Wood, were often controlled by “Boss” Tweed and his Tammany Hall organization. For ten points, name this office held in more recent years by Rudy Giuliani, Michael Bloomberg, and Bill de Blasio.",
      "answer": [
        "Mayor of New York City",
        "Mayor of NYC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Azizul Haque and Hem Chandra Bose subdivided these objects into 1024 types to develop the Henry Classification System of sorting them. Excavating pottery in Japan piqued Henry Fauld’s interest in these objects. Marcello Malpighi documented friction ridges in these structures, which Francis Galton divided into loops, arches, and whorls. For ten points, forensic science studies the identification of what patterns that are unique to every human and often left at crime scenes?",
      "answer": "fingerprints"
    },
    {
      "question": "A series of Reflections on this period were written by Edmund Burke. During this period, the seating arrangements in the National Assembly gave rise to the modern left-right political spectrum. This period led to the execution of thousands of Monarchists and Girondins during the Reign of Terror. Maximilien Robespierre came to prominence during, for ten points, what period of French history that toppled the monarchy?",
      "answer": "French Revolution"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man described the Missouri Compromise as a “firebell in the night” and “deathknell to the Union.” After the USS Philadelphia was captured, this president started America’s first foreign-declared conflict, the First Barbary War. To protect American shipping from the British and French navies, this man signed the Embargo Act. The first man to win a Presidential election as a Democratic-Republican was, for ten points, what third President of the US?",
      "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader, who introduced the aureus, is the subject of a lifesize marble sculpture found in Prima Porta in 1863. The Ara Pacis shows this leader in triumphal procession. This leader adopted the title of divi filius after gaining power 17 years after the murder of Julius Caesar. Along with Marc Antony and Lepidus, he formed the Second Triumvirate. For ten points, name this first emperor of Rome.",
      "answer": [
        "Augustus Caesar or Octavian",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus",
        "Gaius Octavius Thurinus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A banker and a judge who helped draft this treaty were nicknamed the “heavenly twins.” Polish pianist Ignacy Paderewski served as a delegate to this treaty, which left the status of the Teschen district unresolved and demanded the transfer of the regions of Eupen-Malmedy and Saar. This treaty was supervised by the “Big Four”, including Vittorio Orlando, Georges Clemenceau, and David Lloyd George. For ten points, name this peace treaty with Germany that ended World War I.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
    },
    {
      "question": "On his way to this landmark, Umberto Nobile, the pilot of the airship Italia, crashed and was rescued by an international effort. Frederic Cook claimed to have reached this landmark before the person commonly known as its discoverer. The most famous expedition to this landmark was co-led by Matthew Henson and reached it in 1909. For ten points, name this landmark first reached by Captain Robert Peary, who traveled with several Inuit guides.",
      "answer": "North Pole"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Joseph von Eybler and Franz Sussmayr worked to complete an unfinished work by this composer. A legend claims that a masked man, working on behalf of Franz von Walsegg, commissioned that piece from this composer, who became convinced he was writing it for his own funeral. This composer completed work on The Magic Flute a few months before his 1792 death in Vienna. For ten points, name this Austrian composer who first gained fame as a child prodigy.",
        "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mozart was working on this type of musical work, a mass for the dead, at the time of his death.",
        "answer": "Requiem Mass"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In response to this court case, Harry Byrd helped propose the doctrine of “massive resistance”. This decision’s use of the phrase “with all deliberate speed” meant that its provisions were not implemented in some places for decades. Kenneth and Mamie Clark’s experiments with dolls were used as evidence in this case, whose finding was enforced despite Orval Faubus’s resistance at Little Rock Central High School. For ten points, name this Supreme Court decision that ordered the desegregation of public schools.",
        "answer": "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brown v. Board partially overturned this 1896 Supreme Court case, which developed the concept “separate but equal” accommodations.",
        "answer": "Plessy v. Ferguson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the northern terminus of the Natchez Trace. To commemorate the 1897 World’s Fair, this American city constructed a full-scale replica of the Parthenon. Directly east of this city lies an estate called the Hermitage that was the longtime residence of Andrew Jackson. This city on the southern stretch of the Cumberland River contains Music Row and the Country Music Hall of Fame. For ten points, name this capital and most populous city in Tennessee.",
        "answer": "Nashville BONUS:ThisweeklymusicperformancehostedfromNashvillewasbroadcastfromtheRymanAuditorium for many years and is the longest running radio show in the U.S. ANSWER: Grand Ole Opry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This current President of Venezuela was Hugo Chavez’s handpicked successor.",
        "answer": "Nicolas Maduro"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During one of this country’s independence struggles, Jean-Henri Dunant established the International Red Cross after witnessing the Battle of Solferino. In 1860, the Spanish Bourbons were ousted by the Expedition of the Thousand, ensuring the success of this country’s Risorgimento. For ten points, name this country that was unified under Victor Emmanuel II after the 1870 capture of Rome.",
        "answer": "Italy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Expedition of the Thousand forced the Bourbons out of this Italian island, which had been part of a unified kingdom with Naples.",
        "answer": [
          "Sicily",
          "Kingdom of the Two Sicilies"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Samuel Whitside intercepted a group led by Spotted Elk and forced them to encamp at this location. When the deaf Black Coyote refused to surrender his rifle at this location, members of the 7th US Cavalry opened fire. For ten points, name this creek in the Pine Ridge Reservation of South Dakota where, in 1890, hundreds of Lakota Sioux were killed in the largest domestic massacre in American history.",
        "answer": [
          "Wounded Knee Creek",
          "Wounded Knee Massacre"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Controversy erupted after 21 soldiers present at Wounded Knee were presented with this award. Less than 4,000 of these awards have been given.",
        "answer": "Medal of Honor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author of A History of the English-Speaking Peoples coined the term “special relationship.” This politician was replaced by Clement Attlee in a post-war election, then replaced Attlee six years later. One of this man’s speeches described offered his “blood, toil, tears, and sweat” to his country, and another proclaimed that an “Iron Curtain” had descended across Europe. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of Great Britain during World War II.",
        "answer": "Sir Winston Leonard Spencer-Churchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clement Attlee replaced Winston Churchill as Prime Minister when this party won the 1945 elections, the first time it had defeated the Conservatives.",
        "answer": "Labour Party"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Correspondence from this era of history is mapped in a digital project by Dan Edelstein called the Republic of Letters. Immanuel Kant held Frederick II as a ruler typical of this era in his essay “What is [the word that names this era].” A major project in this era comprised of over 70,000 articles; that work was partially compiled by d’Alembert and known as the Encyclopedie. Voltaire was a major figure of, for ten points, what philosophical era largely in the 18th century that challenged religious, social, and political establishments by stressing the use of reason?",
        "answer": [
          "Enlightenment",
          "le si`ecle des lumi`eres"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Frenchman worked with d’Alembert as the primary author of the Encyclopedie.",
        "answer": "Denis Diderot"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "3. 20th Century Dictatorships",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First Secretary of State of the Republic of Texas, who led the state’s colonization and names the state’s capital city.",
          "answer": "Stephen Austin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which Texas won its independence in the 1830s.",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that Texans claimed territory north of; today, it is a large segment of Texas’s southern border.",
          "answer": [
            "Rio Grande",
            "Rio Bravo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "San Antonio mission where James Bowie and Davy Crockett were killed during an 1836 siege.",
          "answer": "the Alamo"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who committed the Goliad Massacre and led the aforementioned 1836 siege against Bowie and Crockett.",
          "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for seizing territory, used by the U.S. to acquire Texas during the administration of James Polk.",
          "answer": [
            "annexation",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive, 18-minute-long battle in the Texan War of Independence won by Sam Houston.",
          "answer": "Battle of San Jacinto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cavalry commander who was the Republic of Texas’s second president.",
          "answer": "Mirabeau Lamar"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Portugal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Portugal for centuries, minus a short stint when the court moved to Brazil.",
          "answer": "Lisbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian-born explorer whose proposed 1492 voyage across the Atlantic was denied funding by the Portuguese.",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus or Cristobal Colon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Natural disaster that struck the Portuguese capital, causing fires and a tsunami in 1755.",
          "answer": "Lisbon earthquake of 1755"
        },
        {
          "question": "First European explorer to sail to India; his travels are recorded in The Lusiads.",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince and explorer who patronized Portuguese exploration and encouraged the conquest of Ceuta [thay-oo-tah].",
          "answer": "Henry the Navigator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Small ship whose lateen sails allowed it to sail down the West African coast.",
          "answer": "caravel"
        },
        {
          "question": "1494 treaty that divided the New World between Castile and Portugal.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Tordesillas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final Portuguese royal house which first held the throne under John IV and later ruled Brazil under two Pedros.",
          "answer": "House of Braganza"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century Dictatorships",
      "prompt": "Given the dictator and other information, name the country, kingdom, empire, etc., that they ruled.",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Il Duce,” [eel doo-chay], Benito Mussolini, during World War II.",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Juan Peron, whose return to Buenos Aires was marred by the Ezeiza massacre.",
          "answer": "Argentina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Getulio Vargas, as well as two decades of general military rule supported by generals in Sao Paulo.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Enver Hoxha [ho-cha], who deposed King Zog from power in Tirana.",
          "answer": "Albania"
        },
        {
          "question": "The author of the “Green Book,” Muammar Gaddafi.",
          "answer": "Libya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fran¸cois and Jean-Claude Duvalier [doo-val-YAY], known as “Papa Doc” and “Baby Doc.”",
          "answer": "Haiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saparmurat Niyazov, who ruled during and after Soviet control.",
          "answer": "Turkmenistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sani Abacha, whose government ordered the hanging of activist Ken Saro-Wiwa.",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was defended by a defensive ring called the Stelling, which overlooked the Zuiderzee. This city’s Grachtengordel neighborhood is a UNESCO World Heritage site. The world’s oldest (20 pts)",
        "stock exchange is located in this city, where Rembrandt’s The Night Watch is located in the (10 pts)",
        "Rijksmuseum [rikes-”museum”]. A famous resident of this city was sent to Bergen Belsen after a raid on the “Secret Annex.” For ten points, name this capital city of the Netherlands."
      ],
      "answer": "Amsterdam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s regime was supported by a volunteer air group led by Claire Chennault. This man, who instituted the White Terror after the February 28 Massacre, was kidnapped by (20 pts)",
        "Zhang Xueliang [chang sheh-lee-ang] and forced to establish a United Front in the Xi’an [shee-an] Incident. Stalin’s control over this man’s son compelled him to permit a Communist (10 pts)",
        "escape in what became the Long March. For ten points, name this leader of the Kuomintang who was defeated by Mao Zedong in the Chinese Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chiang Kai-Shek or Jiang Jieshi",
        "Jiang Zhongzheng"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Production of this foodstuff requires nixtamalization [nish-tamal-ization], a soak-and-boil process using a very alkaline solution, to allow it to release nutrients and be more easily digested. That process was developed around 1500 BC and creates (20 pts)",
        "hominy, which can be ground into masa flour and dough. This grain was first domesticated in (10 pts)",
        "southern Mexico and, with beans and squash, was one of the Three Sisters of Native American agriculture. For ten points, name this grain crop that is also known as maize."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "corn",
        "any type of corn",
        "hominy and/or masa before they are mentioned",
        "maize before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A team in this sport hired Kristi Toliver as an assistant coach; Toliver also plays for Washington’s professional women’s team in this sport, the Mystics. The first full-time (20 pts)",
        "female assistant coach in this sport’s top league was Becky Hammon, who was hired in 2014 as an assistant under (10 pts)",
        "Gregg Popovich. Breanna Stewart, Maya Moore, and Diana Taurasi were college stars at Connecticut in, for ten points, what sport whose women’s league was established in 1997, the same year that Michael Jordan won his fifth title in this sport for the Chicago Bulls?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "basketball",
        "NBA and/or WNBA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this kingdom, the Golden Bull of 1222 was one of a number of acts that regulated the rights of Muslims and Jews. This kingdom expelled the Cuman people before a Mongol invasion, and this kingdom was invaded by the (20 pts)",
        "Ottoman general Kara Mustafa and defeated at the Battle of Mohacs [moh-hotch]. Janos [yahn-osh] Hunyadi ruled this kingdom in the 16th century, before it was (10 pts)",
        "united with Austria. For ten points, name this kingdom that was established by the Magyar people and is now a republic with capital Budapest."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hungary",
        "Magyarorszag"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author wrote about two brothers who flip a coin to determine which one of them will join the Jacobite Rebellion of 1745 in his novel The Master of Ballantrae. In a novel by this author, Alan Breck Stewart joins forces with (20 pts)",
        "David Balfour, who had been sold to a group of passing mariners by his uncle. In another book by this man, the (10 pts)",
        "pirate Long John Silver leads the search for a buried gold. For ten points, name this author of Kidnapped and Treasure Island."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Louis Stevenson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1864, two dozen unarmed Union soldiers were killed in this state’s Centralia Massacre by a mob that included Jesse James. A governor of this state named Lilburn Boggs issued the “extermination order” against the (20 pts)",
        "Mormon church. “Border ruffians” migrated from this state into a neighboring one to promote slavery, and this state’s cities of (10 pts)",
        "St. Joseph and Independence were major starting points of trails leading to the West. For ten points, name this state where the Gateway Arch was built to celebrate St. Louis’s role as a conduit to the West."
      ],
      "answer": "Missouri"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An attempt by traders in this country to be repaid for slaves that they threw off the Zong galvanized its abolition movement. Samuel Sharpe’s Christmas uprising was crushed by this country, which used its West Africa (20 pts)",
        "Squadron to suppress the slave trade after banning it in 1807. When this country banned slavery, the law excluded its (10 pts)",
        "East India Company. Slavery was introduced to the colony of Australia by, for ten points, what country that ended the slave trade under Queen Victoria?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
        "Great Britain",
        "England"
      ]
    }
  ]
}